<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Hievvorth at the funerall of Edmund Warneford Esq. By Thomas Hauskins minister of Gods word. On the 24. of August. 1649.</title>
            <author>Hauskins, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1286_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15019</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859786</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859786</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170663</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170663)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 173:E1286[3], 254:E1286[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Hievvorth at the funerall of Edmund Warneford Esq. By Thomas Hauskins minister of Gods word. On the 24. of August. 1649.</title>
                  <author>Hauskins, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan. 7. 1652"; the second '1' in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library (Early English books) and the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warneford, Edmund, d. 1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, VII, 29-31 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170663:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT HIEWORTH <hi>At the Funerall of</hi> EDMUND WARNEFORD <hi>Eſq.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS HAUSKINS</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>On the 24. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1649.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by H. HALL. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 165<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:170663:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170663:2"/>
            <head>A PRAYER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD be gracious unto thine Handmaid and her little ones, whom by thy ſuddaine ſtroake thou haſt made fatherleſſe and widdow, In the ſence and Conſcience of that Chriſtian duty which as members of the ſame Body wee do owe one to another, we do deſire to grieve with and for them, and in teſtimony thereof in their behalfe to pray, ſaying: O Bleſſed Lord God, as thou haſt ſadly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled thy Handmaid in her outward Condition, ſo do thou truly and ſavingly humble her in her Soule for Sin, which is the moritorious cauſe of all the evills and ſufferings which the Sonnes and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Adam</hi> do feele or feare: and let her ſo weep for the one, as not weeping for the other Bleſſed is the man, and thrice bleſſed is the woman whom thou chaſtneſt, and whom together with the outward cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement thou doſt thus humble and teach them out of thy Law. And foraſmuch as thou haſt promiſed that all things ſhall worke together for good to thoſe that love God: O Lord do thou ſhed abroad thy
<pb facs="tcp:170663:3"/>Love, and the love of Thee into her heart, whereby ſhe may be made capable of the good therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed unto thy ſervants. and then doe thou make a gracious performance and accompliſhment of the ſame: O let this ſore and ſharp loſſe and croſſe be ſo over-ruled and ſanctified by theee, as that it may ſome way or other, yea every way turne to her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good and gaine. It is good for me, ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> to draw neare to thee; it is good may ſhe ſay, and we ſay for her and us all, to draw farther off, as from the Cares, ſo from the comforts of this world, and to draw neare, even neare and nearer both in our affection and in our converſation to thee. O let this heart-piercing affiction drive and draw thy ſervant neare unto thee, nearer and nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in the feare of thee, faith in thee, love toward thee, communion with thee, obedience to thee, and dependence upon thee. In theſe waies, and by theſe means, do thou firſt of all fit her, and then do thou beſtow upon her both inward and outward conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Let her ſo weep as. if ſhee wept not, ſo weep for the loſſe of one comfort, as one that hath not loſt cither all, or the maine of comfort. Let her ſo weep as not to murmure and repine at the dealing of thee the onely wiſe God, and Soveraigne Lord of all, but ſtill let her in faith and patience poſſeſſe thee and her ſelfe, let her ſo weep for the loſſe of a Creature-comfort in a loving husbandas, rejoycing that ſhe hath him the way of beleeving, and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall ever have a faithfull Creator and a
<pb facs="tcp:170663:3"/>moſt loving Saviour. Thou who art the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter of thoſe who are caſt downe, do thou both counſell and comfort her in this tribulation. Let her be able to do all things, and to ſuffer all things, through a <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtrengthening her. Let thy dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, aſſiſting, comforting, ſupporting grace, be ſufficient for her in and againſt her owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and againſt the ſtrength of all adverſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>Lord be thou a Father of all mercies &amp; bleſſings to the Children, who by this ſad hand of Divine providence are become fatherleſſe. O thou juſt and righteous God, what ſhall we who are Parents in our Confeſſions ſay unto thee, but this, to wit, that there is ſin enough in the beſt of Parents, for which thou mighteſt if thou wouldeſt in thy juſt diſpleaſure curſe them, as well in the fruit of their Loines, as of their Labours; in which regard it is the humble and earneſt deſire of every knowing and devout. Parent, that for Chriſt his ſake (who did beare the Croſſe and the Curſe) thou wouldeſt take away the curſe, which is not onely due to them in their owne perſons, but which is moreover due to theirs for their ſake: and this as we hope, was the deſire of the Parent here, when he was alive. In proſecution of which his deſire, he being now departed, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to be laid in duſt, we humbly pray thee, that the good which was in him, may live and dwell, may thrive and grow in his children. But as for the evill which was in him. Oh let it be through
<pb facs="tcp:170663:4"/>the power of thy preventing grace declined by them and through pardoning grace let it not be imputed to them, or viſited upon them. Provide for their education in the knowledge, and faith, and feare of thee, the onely true God, and of Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent. Yea as the ſhall grown in yeares ſo let them grown in all grace, and in ſpeciall in the Love of thee, and under thee in mutuall love and helpfulneſſe each to the other. Now they are forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the father of their fleſh, let is appeare that they are taken up and owned of thee the everlaſting Father, and Father of their ſpirits. Let what is wanting to them be by a good and juſt hand of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in due time ſupplyed, and let what they have be in the meane time, and alwaies by a bleſſing ſanctifyed: whatſoever they have, or whatſoever they want, let them not want a portion of grace from the here, and a portion of glory with thee hereafter.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170663:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 7.29, 30, 31.</bibl>
               <q>But this I ſay brethren, them time is ſhort. I remaineth, that both they that have wives, be a if they had none: And they that weep, as though they wept not and they that rejoyce as though they rejoyced not; and they that buy as though they poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not: And they that uſe this world, as not abuſing it: for the faſhion of this world paſſeth away.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall begin my Sermon with the very words of my <hi>text,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Brethren, the time is ſhort,</hi> the time I meane for my preſent diſcourſe is ſort. for cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, you know, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines me to an houre) It remaineth therefore, that (as perſons who are ſtrainted for want of time) I make ſo much the more haſt, not ſpending one minute of this ſhort time in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impertinent, needleſſe, or complementall circumſtances. And for that cauſe as well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170663:5"/>as others, I ſhall altogether forbeare whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the beginning, or ending of my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to ſpeake in the way of ſuch praiſes and commendations, which any of you doe know, or may think to be due unto the dead, and inſtead thereof I ſhall wholy and ſolely apply my ſelfe unto the end, for which I was requeſted hither, and that is, <hi>To miniſter a word in ſeaſon</hi> for the edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the living, ſuch inſtructions in ſpeciall as are either expreſſed in, or may be dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the words, which I have read unto you.</p>
            <p>I ſhall with a very quick diſpatch as in one, or two minutes paſſe through the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text</hi> to the <hi>text</hi> and then forward. As for the <hi>context</hi> then, this onely I ſhall ſay, <hi>to wit,</hi> That the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the beginning of this chapter doth reſolve certaine Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or caſes propounded to him by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Corinths</hi> concerning marriage and divorce, and from thence he proceeds in the progreſſee of the <hi>chapter</hi> to give counſell and advice to Maſters and Servants: what his reſolves, caveats, &amp; deciſions were in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall caſes propounded, I ſhall referre you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170663:5"/>(as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did the young man in another caſe <hi>Luke.</hi> 10.26.) to what you find written and recorded in the <hi>chapter</hi> it ſelfe, which you may read at your leaſure. Now in the cloſe of theſe deciſions the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayes down &amp; aſſerts a known truth, the knowledge &amp; uſe whereof being of univerſall concernment, he doth therefore direct and exhort all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all ſorts, both marryed and unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, rich and poore, bond and free, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to improve it, and this he doth in the words which I have read unto you; in which words wee have two things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, 1. The preface or introduction <hi>(But this I ſay brethren)</hi> 2. The ſubſtance or maine matter, and that conſiſts in the whole, which followeth.</p>
            <p>The preface or preamble is in theſe words (<hi>this I ſay,</hi> or, this I affirme, or openly avouch) To inſiſt largely upon this preface were to make a buſineſſe of a by-matter, and to reſt, or ſit down in the porch, which was built, for a more ſigtly and convenient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Houſe; and therefore I ſhall lightly paſſe it over, onely by telling you, that the ſcope and end of ſuch preambles,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170663:6"/>or introductions, is to beget the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and exquiſite attention; as if the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> had here ſayd, what was uſuall with <hi>Chriſt</hi> to ſpeake in his Sermons, and what is frequently ſayd by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> to the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia, He, that hath an eare to heare, let him heare.</hi> And let this be the uſe, which I ſhall intreat you to make of this preface, let it awaken and quicken your attention; upon the hearing of theſe words from the mouth of <hi>Saint Paul (This I ſay, brethreen)</hi> I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to be as erect, as attent, as intent, as was <hi>Samuel</hi> upon the calling, and recalling of his name, ſaying, ſpeake brother, ſpeake <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeake Lord, and ſpeake to both eares; for with both eares thy ſervant heareth.</p>
            <p>And let ſo much ſuffice to be ſpoken, as in paſſage to the ſubſtance, or matter of the words, in which are three things conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, firſt <hi>a doctrine,</hi> or an aſſertion <hi>(The time is ſhort)</hi> ſecondly the uſe and application of that doctrine, <hi>(It remaineth, that both they that have Wives, be as if they had none; And &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly a motive, or argument to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, or ſet on the ſayd ſeverall uſes of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170663:6"/>doctrine (<hi>For the faſhion of this world paſſeth away</hi>) The word tranſlated <hi>[faſhion]</hi> is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall, and ſignifies the viſage, out-ſide, accidentall external figure of a thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reall ſubſtance, as if all the things in the world were but a meere ſurface, a vain and empty outſide, &amp; the word tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated <hi>[paſſeth away]</hi> ſignifies likewiſe to cozen, or ſubtily to deceive, ſo that if the words had bin thus rendred, <hi>The viſage of the world deceiveth,</hi> the tranſlation had beene ſufficiently ſuitable to the originall and very agreeable to the truth, and very profitable to edification, it being as well true, that the world doth deceive us, as that the world doth vaniſh &amp; paſſe away; &amp; which of theſe two tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is more agreeable to the <hi>context,</hi> and to the mind of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in this place, ſeemes to me very hard to determine, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if we conſider all circumſtances, which I cannot now ſtand to mention, and much leſſe to debate. Let it be ſufficient to tell, you, that the world doth ſoone vaniſh and paſſe away, and by its ſudden vaniſhing and paſſing away, it doth uſuall cozen &amp; deceive us, and therefore we ſhould <hi>So weep
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170663:7"/>and ſo rejoyce, as if we did not weep and rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are in deed according to diverſities of copies, ſome different readings of the words; but becauſe the differences are very ſmall, <hi>to wit,</hi> about the placeing and point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words, which will not vary the ſenſe, I will not therefore, ſpend any ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this ſhort time in the mentioning, or relating of differences ſo inconſiderable, but will comeforthwith to the doctrine of the <hi>text,</hi> ſet downe in theſe words, <hi>[The time is ſhort]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word tranſlated <hi>[ſhort]</hi> doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſignify Contracted, it being a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor (as ſay the learned in that language) taken from Sailors, who when they draw nigh the ſhore, uſe to contract, or role up their ſailes: or, from a peece of cloth rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up into a little compaſſe, onely a ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the end, ſo that the word accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its ſignificancy might thus be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, <hi>The time is curt</hi> or <hi>curtaild:</hi> and to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify how curt the time is, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth curtaile, or cut ſhort his ſpeech: for the verbe is not expreſſed in the originall (wherein we onely read, the Subſtantive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170663:7"/>and Adjective without the Copulative, <hi>(Time ſhort)</hi> but is left to be underſtood; and it is as if <hi>Saint Paul</hi> had more fully told us, That our time is reduced or brought into a a very narrow conmpaſſe, we having but a ſhort remnant, or ſcantling of time. The doctrine is (as you plainly perceive) like the time, <hi>very ſhort.</hi> If you deſire to have it enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, I ſhall thus deliver it with reference to the <hi>context</hi> in the following words, <hi>to wit, Whatſoever our ſtate, relation, or condition be in this world, whether we be married, or unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, rich, or poore, bond, or free, the time with all of us is but ſhort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doctrine is a truth ſo unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that any one without breach of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, may boldly avouch it in the very phraſe of the <hi>Apoſtie,</hi> ſaying, <hi>This I ſay, the time is ſhort:</hi> &amp; for bare conviction, it is enough to ſay it, without offer of any farther proofe: But becauſe it is both uſual &amp; uſefull, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the making of a due impreſſion upon the affections, not to paſſe over plaine, and confeſſed truths without ſome proofes &amp; illuſtrations from Scripture, I will therefore (not ſo much to convince, as to affect you)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170663:8"/>demonſtrate, and illuſtrate the truth here aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, by declaring in what reſpects <hi>Saint Paul</hi> doth here avouch <hi>the time to be ſhort;</hi> for which purpoſe know you, that <hi>Saint Paul</hi> affirmes <hi>the time to be ſhort</hi> in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, firſt in reſpect of the neere approach of <hi>Chriſts</hi> coming to judgement. Secondly in reſpect of the neare approach of death; I <hi>The time is ſhort betwixt, and the coming of Chriſt to judgment.</hi> There is reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that this is a prime part of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> meaning in the <hi>text:</hi> for beſides that it is the judgment of ſome learned Interpreters, that <hi>Saint Paul</hi> doth immediately aime at this, let is be farther conſidered, that it is ordinary with the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to preſſe <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to duty with arguments taken from the propinquity of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſecond coming; for which, ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. Now if this be the meaning of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in ſaying, that <hi>the time is ſhort, to wit,</hi> That <hi>Chriſt</hi> will ere long come to judgment, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Scriptures, for the confirmation thereof may be alledged <hi>phil.</hi> 4.5.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>lam.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22, 20. There we read, that <hi>The Lords coming draweth nigh, is at hand,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170663:8"/>that <hi>the end of all things is at hand,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt will come quickly &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be objected, that the Saints are ready to thinke and complaine, that it is long ere <hi>Chriſt</hi> will in this ſort come <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. &amp; that they do frequently ſay in reſpect of <hi>Chriſts</hi> coming to them in glory, as <hi>David</hi> ſates in reſpect of <hi>Gods</hi> coming to him in grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2. <hi>Lord when wilt thou come unto me.</hi> I anſwer, that the time betwixt, and <hi>Chriſts</hi> coming to judgment (however in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects long) yet may it be ſayd to be ſhort in the following reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt in reſpect of <hi>Gods</hi> accompt, to whom <hi>a thouſand yeares are but as one day 2 Pet.</hi> 3.8. As <hi>God ſees not, as man ſees,</hi> ſo he reckons not as man reckoneth. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.8.</p>
            <p>Secondly in reſpect of the time already paſt, &amp; in ſpeciall, in reſpect of the time ſince that his coming was prophecied of: for his ſecond coming was prophecied of by <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from Adam, many thouſand yeras agoe <hi>Jud.</hi> 5.14. &amp; in regard hereof our time now is ſaid to be the <hi>the laſt time,</hi> &amp; we are ſaid to be the people, <hi>upon whom the ends
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170663:9"/>of the world are come,</hi> 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 2.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of time to come, if I may ſo ſpeake, and call that time, after which time ſhall be no more: but I meane, that in reſpect of eternity ſucceeding <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſecond coming the time betwixt and that is but ſhort for ſuppoſe it were an 100 or a 1000 yeares afore <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall come to judgment, yet what is that to eternity; it is no more to eternity then a drop of a buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket to the whole Ocean, or then the duſt of a ballance to the vaſt mountaines; it is no more then a finite thing to what is infinite.</p>
            <p>Other conſiderations might be named, with regard whereunto <hi>Chriſts</hi> coming to judgment may be ſayd to be neere at hand; but I ſhall paſſe them over and come to prove the ſecond particular, <hi>to wit,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That the time is ſhort in reſpect of the neare approach of every ones death.</hi> This is another thing, which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> aimes at, in ſaying, that, <hi>the time is ſhort;</hi> he would give us thereby to underſtand, that we have but a ſhort while to live; &amp; for proofe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, view the following Scriptures, <hi>Iob</hi> 14. 1. and 16.22. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 89.47. and 39.12. <hi>Heb.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170663:9"/>13.14. wherein it is ſaid, That <hi>wee are of few daies,</hi> that <hi>we have here no continuing city,</hi> that <hi>wee are Pilgrimes and Strangers &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I make application, I ſhall make anſwer to the following queſtion, <hi>to wit, how ſhort is our time.</hi> Should wee heare ſuch a queſtion undertaken to be anſwered out of the pulpit, we might perhaps at the firſt hearing of it imagine, that the party ſo undertaking did intend to caſt a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and to tell fortune (as we call it) but if you will carefully attend to the three fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing anſwers, which I ſhall make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, I doubt not, but that you will judge it to be a Queſtion not unfit, for the moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſober Divine to reſolve. To the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion then I anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that to ſpeake within ſome latitude, and compaſſe of time, or in generall wiſe, it may well be knowne how ſhort our time is in this ſort, I ſay the ſhortneſte of our time may be knowne by thoſe various Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors, ſimilitudes or compariſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in the following Scriptures, man, his life &amp; daies are ſet forth in the word of <hi>God. Iob.</hi> 7.6, 7. &amp; 9.25, 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.39. &amp; 103.15,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170663:10"/>16. 144, 4. <hi>lam</hi> 4.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.3. There we read, that man, his life and daies are reſembled to <hi>a wind, ſmoake, vapour, graſſe, aflower &amp;c.</hi> Eſpecially I ſhall mention <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5. becauſe that ſcripture comes very neare to the Metaphor, which <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth in the <hi>text;</hi> there wee ſee, That <hi>God</hi> hath rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up our time ſo cloſe and neare together, that there is but the ſcantling of an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bredth leſt unto us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſpeake punctually, to a point or moment of time, there is no man able to ſay; how ſhort the time is, whether in reſpect of <hi>Chriſts,</hi> ſecond coming, or in reſpect of his owne death.</p>
            <p>Firſt, None knoweth the punctuall time, day, or houre, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall come to judgement, and for proofe thereof ſee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.36. &amp;c 25.13. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.35.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, That none knows punctually the time of his owne death, ſee the following Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.1. <hi>lam.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.12. There we read that <hi>mand knowes not his time not ſo much as what shall be on the next morrow &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly I anſwer, that the time is much ſhorter, then the moſt people for the moſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170663:10"/>part are aware of, and this I affirme both in reſpect of death and judgment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the time betwixt this &amp; <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſecond coming, is ſhorter then the moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the moſt part are aware of, may be proved by <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.35. where it is ſaid, that the day of judgement; <hi>shall come as a ſnare upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Inhabitants of the earth,</hi> as alſo by <hi>Lub.</hi> 17.26, 27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where we read, that moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall be as ſenſuall, as ſecure, and as little looking for Chriſts coming to judgment, when he comes as Sodome, or as the old world did expect the deſrtruction of fire, or the deluge of water.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the time betwixt this and our dying day is ſhorter then the moſt doe imagine, may be proved by <hi>Eccle.</hi> 9.12. where it is affirmed, that death comes and ſeizeth upon the moſt of men, even as unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly <hi>as the net, or ſnare doth the Fiſh, or Foule.</hi> The truth of this is ſeen in ſad and frequent experience: for let it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and we ſhall find very commonly, that God doth then cut ſhort the thread of mens lives, at what inſtant they think to live long; <hi>as for example,</hi> when people have undertaken more worldly imployment,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170663:11"/>then ever they did afore, when they have moſt yrons in the fire, and are moſt eager in the purſuit of their worldly deſignes, or when people have compaſſed all their worldly projſects and have go the things, which in their hearts and ſoules they did moſt thirſt after, and do then think to live long &amp; with hearts eaſe upon the ſweet of that which they have laboured ſorely for, &amp; beath their brains about, I ſay, at ſuch a time <hi>God</hi> doth ſhorten and put and end to their time. And for further prooſe hereof, let the following Scriptures be conſidered, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.19, 20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.48.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Uſe</head>
               <p> I now come to the <hi>quod reliquum,</hi> to what remaineth of the doctrine, I meane to the uſe and application of it; and ſurely this that remaineth is like <hi>the good wine in the Goſpel,</hi> though <hi>it comes laſt,</hi> yet indeed <hi>it is beſt of all,</hi> the life and ſoule of a Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the uſe and application of it. Now for the uſe, which we are to make of the foreſaid doctrine, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth in the following words both expreſly and amply, and ſingularly direct us, ſaying, <hi>Let them
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170663:11"/>that have wives be as if they had none, and they that weep &amp;c.</hi> Yet afore I urge or proſecute any of theſe particulars, give me leave to premiſe and inferre one generall uſe, and the rather, becauſe that generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation will have a ſpeciall influence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and will prove as a ſpeciall preparative diſpoſing us the better for the following particuiar inſtructions. Be you then from the conſideration of the foreſaid doctrine in generall wiſe exhorted <hi>To lay to heart the ſhortneſſe of your time.</hi> This is a very ſpeciall and a very profitable duty. <hi>Ecc.</hi> 7.2. There we ſee, that it is the duty of <hi>the living to lay to heart their end:</hi> this laying to heart our end is elſewhere called <hi>the conſideration of our lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, Deut.</hi> 32.29. and in that regard I ſhall both exhort you &amp; pray for you, ſaying in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> words 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. conſider what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath ſaid in the <hi>text</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſhortneſſe of our time, <hi>and the Lord give you underſtanding,</hi> both in this, and <hi>in all things.</hi> We have need of prayer as well as of exhortation: for the Lord knowes, that we do ſee, and heare, and read frequently of many things, which we doe very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170663:12"/>if at all conſider, and lay to heart, and leaſt of all the particular in hand; inſomuch as I may truly ſay, that of any thing in the world, that is ſo well known, ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and apparently ſcene, there is nothing, that is ſo little conſidered and laid to heart. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies in the <hi>text, This! ſay brethren, the time is ſhort;</hi> I may well adde, we our ſelves do ſee, and ſee, and ſee, and ſee often in ſuch fad inſtances and ſpectacles of mortality, as is now before us, That our <hi>time is ſhort:</hi> but who laies to heart and conſiders it who can ſay in this caſe as the <hi>Church</hi> did in another <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.51. <hi>Mine eye affecth my heart?</hi> Let us a little take view of all ſorts and conditions of people. I will paſſe over childhood (becauſe at that age we are leſſe capable of conſideration) and come to youth; <hi>Doe young men and women conſider and lay to heart the ſhortneſſe of their time?</hi> Alas, they are ſo farre from laying to heart any alteration by death, that they lay not to heart any the leaſt alteration by age or ſickneſſe: for young people make not any accompt, that their fine face, their youthfull ſtrength, beauty, activity, ſhall ever decay, or be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170663:12"/>Having paſſed through youth, I come to middle age, and doe aske the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Whether doe people in the midſt of their daies, in the height of their ſtrenght, lay to heart the ſhortnes of their time?</hi> As <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſayd, <hi>Give me a champion, that I may fight with him,</hi> ſo I ſay, ſhew me an inſtance, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in any one man, or woman, who conſiders this thing, that I may commend them. Yea to come to old age, <hi>doe people when they are wll ſtricken in yeares,</hi> or <hi>when they begin to be ſickly and doe find infirmities to be growing upon them, doe they lay to hears the ſhortneſſe of their time.</hi> Alas the very Heathen did obſerve this corruption; and deceit in the heart of man, <hi>to wit</hi> that there is ſcarce any one ſo old, but he thinks to live one yeare longer, and ſtill one yeare longer, and yet one years long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. for people when they begin to be ſick, and as we our ſelves may obſerve, how it is given to people to thinke, and ſay of their ſickneſſes, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that of Lazarus, <hi>This ſickneſſe is not unto death;</hi> yea it were to be wiſhed, that carnall friends in their fooliſh pity, [com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170663:13"/>to viſit their ſicke friends] would not, like the falſe Prophets of old crying <hi>peace, peace,</hi> ſow the pillowes of ſecurity under their freinds arme-holes, and rocke them in the cradle of forgetfullneſſe both of <hi>God</hi> and of themſelves, aſſuring their friends, that their preſent ſickneſſe ſhall not ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and much leſſe end their time; of ſuch friends we may well ſay as <hi>Iob</hi> did of his, <hi>Miſerable Counſellers and miſerable Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are yee all.</hi> And becauſe it is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to accuſe, unleſſe the charge be made evident, I will now make it appeare by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry evidences, that very few doe lay to heart <hi>the shortneſſe of their time;</hi> Firſt I ſhall bring in the common wickedneſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneſſe of the world to teſtify it, and I ſhall ſay with alluſion to thoſe words of <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.14. If the moſt of people doe indeed conſider and lay to hart <hi>the ſhortneſſe of their time,</hi> what meanes that common cry of all forts of ſinnes (of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, ſwearing, curſing, unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe,) which we doe daily ſee with our eyes and heare with our eares, eſpecially if we goe abroad to a market, fayre, or the like.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170663:13"/>
               <p> But for more particular evidence I ſay, firſt, as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeakes in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.10. ſo I ſay here, <hi>The pride of people doth teſtifie to their faces,</hi> that they doe not lay to heart <hi>how ſhort their time is:</hi> for did people conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and ſadly the <hi>ſhortneſſe of their time,</hi> would they be ſo haughty, ſo hofty, ſo ſcornefull and diſdainfull of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours: (as if we all were not one fleſh, and of the ſame blood) as they be. Would the women kind be of ſuch a proud demeanour as is deſcribed and reproved, in <hi>the haughty Daughters of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, walking with ſtretched out necks, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton eyes, mincing as they goe and making a tinckling with their feete. Eſa.</hi> 3.16 Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved, the minding of <hi>the ſhortneſſe of our time,</hi> would bring downe the ſtout hearts and lofty lookes of people, and would cauſe us all to walke more humbly both with our <hi>Creator</hi> and with our fellow-creatures</p>
               <p>Secondly, Mens covetouſneſſe doth teſtify to their faces, that they lay not to heart <hi>the shortneſſe of their time:</hi> we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170663:14"/>ſee, that with very many there is no end of wordly care, toile and travell, they being never ſatisfied in their minds with what they have, but are ſtill reſtleſſe in adding houſe to houſe, field to field, farme to farme, bargaine to bargaine. Did people ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they have not long to live, there would be more contentment and leſſe convetuoſneſſe, then is every where among all ſorts to be ſeene.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That few doe conſider <hi>the shortneſſe of their time</hi> doth appeare by this, <hi>to wit,</hi> That though people doe ſometimes think upon death, yet they think onely of one way of dying, or upon one kind of death, <hi>to wit,</hi> they think only of dying a naturall death, they think of dying by age, or in their beds; where as we may as well dy an untimely, or a violent death as a naturall death, we may be cut off in the midſt of our daies and ſtrengthy by a thouſand diſaſters, we may die in a priſon, we may have our throats cut, or our braines daſht out, we may die in a ditch as well as in our beds.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170663:14"/>
               <p> Fourthy, It appears, that the, moſt people are mindleſſe of <hi>the shortneſſe of their time,</hi> in that they conſider not in whoſe hands their time is: For whereas Scripture tels us, that our time is in Gods hands, and that our life doth wholy depend upon his pleaſure and appointment, they are as forgetfull of any ſuch thing (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by their common language) as thoſe wordlings, whom Saint <hi>Iames</hi> reproveth for projecting this and that, and yet never asking leave of God <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.13, 14.</p>
               <p>Fiftly It appeares, in that people doe ſo buſy themſelves about trifles with neglect of the maine things neceſſary. How doe the moſt people firſt provide for the body, for the things of the world, and put off the providing for the ſoule and things belonging to another world, I will inſtance onely in two things of moment, which people do put off.</p>
               <p>Firſt the making of their wils. We ſee in experience, how that people doe commonly put off the doing of this to the time of their ſickneſſe (albeit it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170663:15"/>is moſt uncertaine, whether they ſhall have any warning of death by ſickneſſe) yea many will not doe it, when they are ſicke, unleſſe they are perſwaded, that they ſhall die of their fickneſſe and how few will perſwade themſelves, or will ſuffer themſelves to be perſwaded by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that when they are ſick, they are ſicke to death.</p>
               <p>Secondly, But this is a light matter in compariſon: in alluſion to thoſe words of the <hi>Prophet</hi> to the king <hi>Eſa.</hi> 7.13. I ſay here, that <hi>it is a light matter</hi> for men to neglect the making of their wills, and thereby to prejudice their poſterity; there are matters of farre greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are commonly neglected, and thoſe are, The repenting of our ſins, the amendment of our waies, the ſetting of accompts betwixt God and our ſoules, the making of our peace with God our Judge, the making of our calling and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure, and alas, alas, how are theſe neglected? Let two things be here obſerved, I How laſie and ſlow and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh the moſt of people are as to theſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170663:15"/>things; they are as loath to come to any buſineſſe of this nature, as ever any ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard was to riſe out of his bed, inſomuch as when they are awaked by the loud cries of Gods Miniſters, calling to and upon them in thoſe words of <hi>Solemon Prov.</hi> 6.19. <hi>How long wilt thou ſleepe O ſluggard, when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They do yawn and ſtretch them ſelves upon the bed of ſecurity and ſenſuallity, ſaying with that <hi>Sluggard Prov.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Yet a little ſleepe, a little ſlumber, alittle folding of the hands to ſleepe;</hi> a little more of the pleaſures of ſin, a little more of the profits of ſin &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Secondly, let it be obſerved, how faithleſſe and falſe hearted people are in things of this nature: for albeit they will purpoſe and ſet a time for the doing of theſe things, yet when the time comes, yet (<hi>faithleſſe &amp; perverſe generation</hi> as they are) they will put it of till another time. Wee ſee in experience, that <hi>Laban</hi> did not more often change <hi>lacobs</hi> wages, then many men and women have contrary to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170663:16"/>their purpoſes, promiſes, vowes and covenants changed the time of their repentance and converſion; they have ſet a time ten times over, &amp; that time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt and gone, they are ſtill to repent and convert, yea they are as farre (if not farther) from repenting and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as ever they were afore.</p>
               <p>Briefly and undeniably, The whole courſe of peoples lives doth teſtifie to their faces, that <hi>the ſhortneſſe of their time</hi> is not laid to heart by them: for conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether the moſt people doe not live, even as the drunkard drinks, or as the prodigall ſpends; as thoſe doe drinke and ſpend as if they could never ſee the bottome of the barrell, or of their patrimony, ſo people doe ſo live, as if they were to live for ever in this world, as if they ſhould never come to the end of their lives</p>
               <p>Having now ended my generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, I might in the next place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre ſundry particular ones: <hi>For example,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, If our time be ſhort, then let us all looke back and conſider, how we have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170663:16"/>ſpent and miſ-ſpent our time, what time we have loſt.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, Learne the miſerie and miſchiefe of delayes of delaying things of moment.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, Beware of a ſurprizall, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caught napping (as we uſe to ſay) of being taken at unawares.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, Labour leſſe for the meat that periſheth, and labour more for that which endureth to everlaſting life.</item>
                     <item>Fifthly, Learne this point of wiſdome, <hi>to wit,</hi> to diſpatch the moſt neceſſarie things in the firſt place.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and the like inſtructions might fitly be deduced from the doctrine in hand, and are very profitabe to be urged, but becauſe I deſire to ſpeake ſomewhat to ſome of the uſes, which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth expreſsly inferre from the point, I muſt therefore of neceſſitie forbeare the proſecution of any of the ſaid particulars.</p>
               <p>The firſt uſe, which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth make of this doctrine is to married per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; I ſay to married perſons: for what he ſaies to Hushands, ſaying <hi>[let them,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170663:17"/>that have wives be as if they had none]</hi> muſt be underſtood as ſpoken likewiſe to wives (for as they who have wives muſt live as if they had none, ſo for a like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thoſe who have husbands muſt live as if they had none) The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> true and full meaning is, That the ſhortneſſe of the time conſidered, thoſe who are married ſhould ſo live as if they were looſed, or unmarried. But ſome will here perhaps demaund this queſtion, <hi>what muſt married perſons do,</hi> or <hi>how muſt they ſo live married, as if they were unmarried.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere, that divers particular du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are therein comprized; among which I ſhall inſtance onely in three, or foure.</p>
               <p>Firſt it implies, that man and wife ought ſo to live together, as making a certaine accompt, that within a verie ſhort time they muſt part, or be parted aſunder, ſaying that <hi>[de futuro]</hi> for future concerning each other, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid <hi>[De praeſenti]</hi> to the Samaritan woman con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her reputed husband, He, whom I now have, ſhall not alwaies be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170663:17"/>my Husband, She whom I now have, ſhall not alwaies be my wife. The contrary preſumption, or forgetfulneſſe is (I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid) the common fault of married per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: for conſider whether it be not with the moſt couples, as you ſhall immediatly hear from me; every one doth eagerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a good wife or husband, being halfe impatient for ſuch a bleſſing; as was <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> for the bleſſing of Children, ſaying, A good husband, a good wife, or elſe I am undone; and when God hath granted unto men &amp; women theſe their deſires, what doe they think, or ſay, and how are they affected. They are affected as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> was, when he had got a gourd, they are glad out of meaſure, ſaying as <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea</hi> in another caſe, <hi>I am rich and increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in comfort, and I have need of nothing,</hi> yea ſaying moreover as <hi>Babylon</hi> in her proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie <hi>Eſa</hi> 47.8. I am made and I am made for ever, I ſhall never be a widow &amp;c. and thence it is, that God making a ſudden and unexpected alteration, they are as much overwhelmed with ſorrow and amazement, as afore they were full
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170663:18"/>and did overflow with joy; juſt as it was with <hi>Ionah,</hi> ſo it is with them; for as <hi>Ionah</hi> was over-joyed when he had a Gourd and when he was ſuddenly depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of it, he did ſo take it to heart, as that he wiſhed his owne death, ſo they being over-joyed in the enjoyment one of another, when God hath made a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they are ſo out of meaſure paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and impatient, as to wiſh, that they had died the ſame day, and been bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the ſame grave with them. But would you know your duty; remember then this firſt particular from the <hi>text, to wit,</hi> That you are ſo to live together in the married eſtate, as making account, that it cannot alwaies, yea, that it cannot long be ſo, but that within <hi>a ſhort time</hi> you muſt part. Man and wife muſt ſoe live in the Hourſe as the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> did in the world, <hi>to wit,</hi> as <hi>ſtrangers and ſojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> together <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13, 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Would man and wife ſo live mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, as unmarried, they muſt be carefull to uſe all the comforts and contents of marriage ſoberly and moderately. It is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170663:18"/>one maine part of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> end and ſcope in theſe words, to exhort all marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons unto Chriſtian ſobrietie and moderation in the uſe of all mariage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments, ſo that they may be wings but not weights unto them, we may ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer as well of the comforts as of the cares of this life.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That man and wife may ſo live married as if they were unmarried, they muſt have a ſpeciall care not to coole or abate in affection to the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> We muſt ſtill love the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in ſuch ſort, as if we had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Love</hi> but him. The law of marriage is for the married perſons to forſake fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, and to cleave to each other, but it is not to forſake the Lord <hi>Chriſt.</hi> This admonition is the rather needfull, becauſe of the common fault of very many married couples in the world. We do live in a world of extremes both within doores and without: for as ſome couples do love too little, and ſearſe at all, ſo others do love one another too much, in ſo much as that they do quite
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170663:19"/>dote one upon another, &amp; make idols one of another, they love one another as <hi>Eli</hi> did his ſonnes, <hi>to wis,</hi> more then they love God their Maker, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> their Redeemer. God may have the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie againſt many married perſons as he had againſt <hi>Epheſus, to wit,</hi> That they have loſt much of their firſt love to him. But oh that married perſons would remember, that God is a Jealous God; And oh that they would remember thoſe words of <hi>Chriſt Mat.</hi> 10.37. He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth Father, or Mother, Sonne, or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Hhusband, or Wife, more then <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is unworthy of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might here have added certained o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particulars, but that I haſten to ſpeak a few words concerning the next parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, <hi>And they that weep as if they wept not.</hi> Let the queſtion be demanded, <hi>what is it for a Chriſtian ſo to weep, for a loſſe, or croſſe, as if hee wept not.</hi> I anſwer, 1. A Chriſtian muſt ſo weep for his ſinnes, which are the meritorious cauſe of every loſſe and croſſe, as not weeping for the loſſe, and croſſe it ſelſe. Our ſorrows in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170663:19"/>reſpect of any ſuffering ſhould be nothing in compariſon of our ſinnes that have deſerved it. I cannot ſay indeed, tha it is the ſcope of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the <hi>text</hi> to preſſe the belceving Corinths to ſorrow for ſinne above all things, nevertheleſſe I have thought good to anſwer the Queſtion in this ſort, in the firſt place partly becauſe it is a true ſaying, That a Chriſtian ought ſo to weep for his ſinnes as not weeping for his ſufferings (for our ſufferings we muſt ſo weep, as not weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but for our ſinnes we muſt ſo weep, as it we wept indeed) and partly becauſe thoſe perſons, who do truly, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully weep for their ſinnes, cannot chooſe but weep moderately for any outward ſuffering, which faid, moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the ſcope of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the <hi>text.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Would we ſo weep as not weeping, we muſt ſo weep, as not to refuſe ſuch Chriſtian counſell, or comfort as is fit to be given to us in our mournfull condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When people are under the heavy hand of God, they are more ſit to be ſpoken unto, then when they thrive and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170663:20"/>proſper in the world; and one cauſe why <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us, that <hi>ſorrow is better then laughter,</hi> is becauſe (ſaies he) <hi>by the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the countenance the heart is made better,</hi> more ſoft, and more humble <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.3. We ſhould therefore ſo weep, as that we do not refuſe ſuch Chriſtian ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, counſell, or comfort, as it fit to be given unto perſons in our ſad condition. The contrary exceſſe is a fault too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; for many weep for their loſſes, as <hi>Rachel</hi> did for the loſſe of her children <hi>[they will not be comforted]</hi> or as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did for their bondage <hi>[They harkned not unto Moſes for anguiſh of heart, Exod.</hi> 6.9.]</p>
               <p n="3">3. That we may ſo weep as not weeping, we muſt ſo weep as not to murmure, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, or once to open our mouthes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord and his dealing; wee muſt ſo weep as quietly, ſilently, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſubmitting our ſelves to the diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the only wiſe God and Soveraigne Lord of all. I ſhall for this referre you to ſuch Scriptures as wherein patience under all loſſes and croſſes is as a very ſpeciall and Chriſtian vertue, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170663:20"/>and wherein the contrary evils of fretting, murmuring, and repining, are forbidden, as very great &amp; grievous evils.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That we may ſo weep as not weeping, we muſt ſo weep as not to diſhonour our Religion and ſpecially that faith and hope, which we profeſſe to have in God. It is a great ſinne and ſhame for a Chriſtian to mourne exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively for any outward ſuffring for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth diſhonour religion, and give the world occaſion to think, that there is no ſuch comfort in the word and in the waies of God as the Scriptures do teſtifie, &amp; therfore we ſhould beware of ſo mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as to do the leaſt diſhonour unto religion, by bringing an evill report up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
               <p>And more eſpecially we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of ſo mourning as to diſhonour our faith and hope in God, either that hope, which we profeſſe to have either touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves, or touching any of our departed friends.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we ſhould ſo weep for the dead, for any of our departed friends as not to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170663:21"/>diſhonour, or diſparage that hope, which we profeſſe to have concerning them and their better condition in another world; we ſhould ſo mourne, that they are loſt to us and to the comfort which we might have had by them here, as not mourning, that they are loſt to God and to themſelves; we ſhould ſo mourne for them being dead, as rejoicing, that they are alive to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that one day they ſhall riſe againe to life everlaſting. This is the <hi>Apoſtlles</hi> counſell concerning the manner, or meaſure of mourning for the dead, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.13.</p>
               <p>Secondly and laſtly, we ſhould ſo mourne as not to diſhonour that faith and hope, which we do profeſſe to have in God, his love &amp; favour. Every true Saint and ſervant of God is moſt deeply, moſt highly in the love &amp; favour of God (as the Scriptures do teſtiſie) and they cannot be under ſuch ſadneſſe for any outward loſſe and croſſe, but that ſtil they have abundant cauſe to rejoice in the intereſts, which they have in the favour &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in ſo much
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170663:21"/>as that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> may well ſay to his over ſad and penſive ſervants, as <hi>Elka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> did to his beloved <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Why weepeſt thou and why is thy heart</hi> ſo much, ſo over much <hi>grieved, am not I bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to thee then ten ſons.</hi> Is not my love better then the love of ten husbands, or ten wives. Briefly then, upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of weeping, a Chriſtian muſt of weep for the loſſe of one comfort, as not weeping, but rejoycing rather that he hath not loſt all, nor the maine of comſorts, A wife muſt ſo weep for the loſſe of a loving Husband, as not weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but rejoycing rather, that ſhee hath not loſt an ever living God and an ever loving Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caution.</hi> As <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid in another caſe, ſo I ſay here, All men and women can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive this comfort, but onely thoſe, to whom it is given, I meane, the true Saints and ſervants and children of God, ſuch as can ſay with the ſpouſe in the <hi>Canticles (I am my welbeloveds and my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved is mine)</hi> and therefore <hi>Qui poteſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, capiat,)</hi> They that can receive this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170663:22"/>comfort as belonging to them, let them and them alone receive it, but as for worldlings and the wicked (continuing in the eſtate wherein they are) I muſt needs ſay, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did to the rich <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.24. <hi>Woe unto you for you have received your conſolation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170663:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
